Finding Aid for Alexander Winchell Papers relating to Syracuse University, 1850-1896.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alexander Winchell Papers relating to Syracuse University 1850-1896 1871-1880
Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
7 microfilm reels
90158 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Alexander Winchell was a professor of geology and paleontology at the University of Michigan and director of the Michigan Geological Survey. In 1872 he was appointed the first Chancellor of Syracuse University. He was inaugurated on February 13, 1873 and resigned on June 24, 1874.
These selections of the Alexander Winchell papers relate primarily to his chancellorship at Syracuse University (1873-1874) and to the years following. The materials were microfilmed at the request of a researcher.
Subjects:
Syracuse University.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
- Correspondence
  - 1873-1879 (Reel 1)
  - July 1850-September 1896, not addressed to Alexander Winchell (Reel 1)
- Biographical and miscellaneous
  - Miscellanea (Reel 1)
  - Family record and short biographical sketch of Alexander Winchell (Reel 1)
  - Biographical sketch of Alexander Winchell, 1824-1886 (Reel 1)
- Speeches, lectures and miscellaneous writings
  - February 12, 1873: Remarks to the medical graduates (Reel 1)
  - September 24, 1873: Report of the Syracuse University to the Western New York Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church (Reel 1)
  - January 1, 1875: Syllabus of a course of lectures on geology to be delivered in the Syracuse University during the winter term of 1874-1875 (Reel 1)
  - September 1, 1875: School of Geology in the Syracuse University (Reel 1)
  - August, 1876: Observations on the Chautauqua Conglomerate (Reel 1)
- Diaries
  The volume numbers refer to the numbering sequence originally applied to the original Winchell collection.
  - 1872 (vol. 93) (Reel 1)
  - 1873 (vol. 94) (Reel 1)
  - 1874 (vol. 95-96) (Reel 1)
  - 1875 (vol. 97) (Reel 2)
  - 1876 (vol. 98) (Reel 2)
  - 1877 (vol. 99) (Reel 2)
  - 1878 (vol. 100) (Reel 2)
  - 1879 (vol. 101) (Reel 2)
  - 1880 (vol. 102) (Reel 2)
  - 1873 of trip to Europe (vol. 114-117) (Reel 2)
  - 1873-1874 (vol. 118) (Reel 2)
  - 1874 containing notes and thoughts on Lotie (vol. 119) (Reel 2)
  - 1874 of trip to Europe (vol. 120-125) (Reel 2)
  - 1875 of travels through United States (vol. 126-128) (Reel 2)
  - 1875 of trip to Boston and New York (vol. 129-131) (Reel 2)
  - 1876 of trip to Centennial Exposition (vol. 132) (Reel 2)
- Travel Diaries
  - 1876 (vol. 133-134) (Reel 2)
  - 1877 (vol. 135) (Reel 2)
  - 1878 (vol. 136) (Reel 2)
  - 1879 (vol. 137-138) (Reel 2)
  - 1879-1880 (vol. 139) (Reel 2)
- Letterpress books
  - 1871-1874 (vol. 156) (Reel 3)
  - 1874-1877 (vol. 157) (Reel 3)
  - 1874-1877 (vol. 157) (cont.) (Reel 4)
  - 1877 (vol. 158) (Reel 4)
  - 1877-1881 (vol. 159) (Reel 4)
  - 1887-1881 (vol. 159) (cont.) (Reel 5)
  - 1877-1878 (vol. 160) (Reel 5)
  - 1877-1878 (vol. 160) (cont.) (Reel 6)
- Various volumes
  - Volume, 1873-1874 containing copies of European travel letters from Winchell family members (vol. 169) (Reel 6)
  - Record of Correspondence
    - 1871-1877 (vol. 174) (Reel 6)
    - 1877-1883 (vol. 175) (Reel 6)
  - Geological Lectures
    - 1870 (vol. 196) (Reel 6)
    - 1875 (vol. 197) (Reel 6)
  - Register of Pupils, 1873-1879 (vol. 237-partial) (Reel 6)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1873-1876 concerning Syracuse University (vol. 261) (Reel 6)
  - 1873-1874 concerning European travels (vol. 262) (Reel 7)
  - 1876-1879 (vol. 266) (Reel 7)